All right, it's November 11th, 2025.
This is a little bit of a preview and a
walk through for the 5th applied active
inference symposium happening from 12th
to the 14th of November for the YouTube
viewers, listeners out there and to give
a little visual overview. So here I am
in the program which is a link that has
been sent to you by email if you
registered and in the video description.
Top page has some overall information
about the symposium. It's online. It's
free. There's no need to register at
this point. Same material is available
after the fact. Presenters
links to the abstract book. Here is a
PDF that you can download. Blocked in my
browser, but a Zenoto publication with
the abstract book.
And the first table is the card view of
the presenters, the keynote address by
Carl Fristen,
those who will be presenting in the live
stream sessions,
some more tool oriented workshops,
and those who have submitted a
pre-recorded
video, and that will also be played on
the live stream, but just to be clear
that those are pre-recorded.
This next table is a timeline view.
Let's make it a little more visible.
So, here is a chart view,
different sessions in different times,
and then the abstract table
for each of the presentations.
All right, back to the first page.
That's what you can expect to see.
There's some more pages. Um, there's a
first, if you want to watch the live
streams, those are the embedded YouTube
videos here or they're linked out there
or you can watch it directly in KOD. Uh,
more links, there is public
participants. So this is on the
registration form. We asked whether
people were okay with sharing their
responses publicly and for those people
are represented in this table. There's
also the GitHub active inference
institute symposium repo and if you run
the symposium.sh SH script, you get a
terminal option
checks your environment.
Then you can list available data,
analyze the 2025 participants, generate
summaries of the columns and the
different questions, create background
research, personalized curriculum, and
some visualizations that are across the
whole cohort. So here in data input
AF2025
this is the public data table that is
available here which maybe at the end of
this short stream we'll look through
manually and then the outcomes are of
two different kinds there are
visualizations that have the PCA
embeddings and some other simple
language analyses
and then there are the uh column
summaries. So these are LLM generated
summaries of some of the columns that
we'll look at and there are the people
folders. So people folders have uh they
use methods in this repo for open router
and for perplexity calls
using perplexity with internet research
and LLM. There's a background file on
each participant with their public
information. So here's bird to fry
and then there is we can see how good or
useful this is but as a sort of
appetizer for [snorts]
generative AI and education uh profile
analysis and curriculum personalized
development. So just just as an example,
there's other repos at the institute not
going to be explored here with more
tuning on custom curriculum, but fun way
to look within and across different
participants
um areas of interest
and we'll we'll look more at that
because I haven't looked through this
table and maybe there's some fun things
to talk about.
Uh join the institute discord to chat
with others. You can jump into the voice
chat at any time during the symposium or
otherwise and we can continue the
discussion asynchronously. Here's the
GitHub repo
with all of the uh methods for
generating
the personalized
curriculum in the background and the
visualizations.
There is a 3D
adventure space which Pablo's session is
going to go into more detail in. Let it
load in the background a little bit.
Oh, let it load on the side.
Interesting.
uh more information on the institute
ecosystem previous symposium some more
general links and other pages here
symposium program top level that's all
the links that you want presenters
that is the tables we looked at
registration data doesn't really matter
at this point so I'll hide it public
participants we'll look through that and
then the sponsors
navig Navigating uncertainty with Anna
Prairaa and Upcycle Club by Heros Neo2
and we'll acknowledge them in the
opening live stream as well. And then
the last tab is more information about
the institute. Um here is a 3D space.
Pablo's session is going to go into more
detail on on this session and what they
did at um their game development
approach that they took here.
Um
just in closing while we leave that
figure 7.3
partially visible
these questions that are asked in the
public participant registration form
person's affiliations and contact
details their background
first question here what would be useful
for you in the symposium pragmatic value
what would be interesting or informative
ative for you to learn from the
symposium. Epistemic value.
How are you applying active inference?
We'll move that to the first question.
What are the biggest hurdles or
challenges facing active inference
research?
What would help you learn and apply?
How did you hear about the symposium?
How could active inference applications
make impact in 2026?
Any other comments?
So let's uh and and those are summarized
in wordclouds and in LLM response. So
uh for example the summary
of this first question, how are you
applying active inference? What domain
or stage? that is summarized in the
outputs column summaries
first markdown
summary information on the question and
then some summaries. So
to the extent these are public and
there's other information that one could
draw on as well. This is one way to
summarize some perspectives and
different things people are working on,
different challenges people are having.
Um, what would be useful for you in the
symposium? Introduction,
academic and industry context,
conceptual upskilling, seeing how active
inference is applied,
broad sampling,
insight into tools for robotics,
design reviews,
follow up on IY, references to papers,
contact data. Okay. What would be
interesting or informative?
software basing mechanics. See what
other companies are doing.
Clear statement of how active inference
is the basis for wholly new AI and how
LLMs or SLMs can be integrated into
active inference-based AI.
Examples of how active inference can
frame non-human systems.
Proven studies,
practical demonstrations, collaborative
exercises showing how to operationalize
active inference in real world context,
especially in education, science,
communication, and AI assisted
reasoning.
Current applications and methods, basic
introduction to modeling. Cool. Okay.
What are the biggest hurdles or
challenges facing active inference
research and application?
Collaboration and noise in the AI arena.
People guarded and cautious about
generalizing claims rightfully so. But
epistemological squashing squishing is
happening at a time when we should be
openly discussing and exploring
together.
It may not yet be so clear what active
inference can offer to traditional
academic disciplines and established
university departments.
There's much rhetoric around the
non-refutability of active inference
framework that it is a useful metaphor
only that brains don't compute etc. The
apparently sparse empirical support so
far is problematic but there remains the
practical and experimental barriers to
finding a killer theory prediction data
support reputation instance.
It would be good
to have a clear road map to its
potential impact in creating novel
clinical interventions. So I would be
excited to know how this is progressing.
Wow. So so many things to read in this
showcase against current methods.
Don't know enough of scope to have an
opinion.
Make connections between software
methods and specific applications.
Critical mass of practice to be
understood.
Bridging theory and practical
implementation.
Good question. will consider awareness,
coordinating with domain experts with
quantitative methods, finding
researchers that are geographically
close to me. Okay. What would help you
learn and apply? Active inference. This
is where hopefully there's already an
existing resource from the institute or
out there in the ecosystem or it's kind
of like a target that this is like
something else somebody is searching
for, foraging for. So collaboration
opportunities
market education on active inference to
developers online course or resource
tools and resources resources and tools
tools and shared research questions
textbook group minor mentorship discuss
what I learn and get feedback on ideas
and prototypes. some bimonthly cadence
to update on research project online
community directory also K12 level
educational materials working examples
in Python shared open source funds to
free up time to think and learn and
tools a group for shared interest and
active inference and mentor to evaluate
progress semiformal languages in which
to describe conceptual models
learning by coding open- source factor
graphs tools and resources resource and
tools.
I am new to active inference and want to
get a feel for the field. Information,
collaborations, tools,
tutorials, applications, practical
toolkits, simulation environments,
engineering playbook, edge first
reference stack, benchmarks for identity
and security, working group on identity
and security, executive primers,
resource and tool,
computational tutorial, guey based RX
infer type app with clear instructions
on how to build generative models
compatible with active inference and
estimate them using data. [sighs]
Okay.
And last piece on this short stream and
then I'll check the chat at the end.
How could active inference applications
make impact in 2026? Think big. [gasps]
I think active inference genuinely
offers a path to a more elegant and
organic form of AI that will serve the
synergy between humans and machines far
better than the one that destroys the
planet by adding more legs to a
caterpillar hoping it will fly. I see
nuance definition of non-marovian as a
non-dual field integral not a linear
chain of more nests change the way we
think about moral problems in and out
groups.
I could imagine active inference having
a big impact in 2026 if a simplified
model existed that people outside of
academia could engage with.
We are in the early stages of developing
novel clinical approaches.
Theoretical advancing understanding of
motor learning and motor control
including motor impairment.
More popularization in science press
increase agentic automation performance
by enabling LLMs to be uncertain about
gaps in world model and first ask
questions to reduce uncertainty via free
energy principle before providing a
solution or begin an automation process.
Formalize metastability based theories
of chronic pain. I'm very interested in
peace research which is high demand in
agents for responsible case management
in public sector.
Educational technology that adapts to
individual learning styles.
Reducing the cost of inference through
organic emergent systems of
self-representation and problem
space-time navigation. Thereby greatly
reducing the barriers to entry for
lesser resource communities to benefit
from the boon of artificial
intelligence.
Active inference could shift the AI
paradigm from optimization to
self-organization.
If we crack productionready tooling,
active inference could become the
framework for building actual autonomous
agents. Not LLM with tool calling, but
systems that maintain world models and
plan.
models could change the world through
simulating and testing counterfactual
events, providing insights into
scientific discovery, treatment,
interventions, policy.
The breadth of the active inference
framework provides this broad scope and
fostering of interdisciplinary
collaboration.
Make easier the bolts framing
connections among nature, human
organization, AI, computational
intelligence as overall architecture of
disorder management.
business, operating, legal, technical,
social bolts. We need to think about
human centric value generation,
highlighting key application domains,
and publishing a high-profile paper
by announcing a strategy to unite
smaller nations, AI hubs, family
offices, foundations, institutes,
associations, and alliances to build the
next big thing in AI with active
inference, a key part of multimodal,
edge focused, highly efficient,
regenerative AI.
raising awareness of potential uses in
AI application spatial web by creating
empathetic AI systems, adaptive learning
environments, and decentralized agents
capable of self-regulation and social
cooperation.
Our core effort is understanding what
active inference really is.
Provide agentic alternatives to LLM.
Active inference could be applied to
critique and improve the foundations of
active inference recursively.
Change the world. Study love and social
dynamics from first principles to
support access of active inference
framework to establish professors with
active post and projects. How AI is used
by regul network machines.
link research models to practitioners to
impact policy. So that is just a few
pieces of it. Hopefully this is a bit of
the flavor for participating in it.
There will be those live streams. There
will be fun play in this space, the
Discord for chat and lots of ways to get
involved to
improve the symposium every year. So
thanks for watching. Thank you up club
for supporting and you wrote very much
looking forward to the symposium indeed.
So am I/we.
See you later. Thank you. Bye.